Guide to the Phytotron Records, 1958 - 1984 UA.25.11.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Phytotron records
1958 - 1984
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Botany
UA.25.11.0001
6 Linear Feet
Established in 1968 with funds from Duke and the National Science Foundation (NSF), the Phytotron is a controlled environment research facility located on the Duke University campus housing plant growth chambers, controlled greenhouses, and associated instrumentation and laboratories. The Phytotron Records contain correspondence, memoranda, financial records, reports, grant proposals, blueprints, schematics, contracts, supplier catalogs, specification books, and other records of the planning, construction, and operation of the facility. Major subjects include the Duke University Dept. of Botany and Dept. of Biology, greenhouses, and global environmental change. English.
4,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice required for use.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Phytotron Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980 and 1993.
Historical Note
The Phytotron is a controlled environment facility located on the Duke University campus. It houses 48 plant growth chambers and six controlled greenhouses -- a total of over 450 square meters of growth space -- and associated instrumentation and laboratories. Established in 1968 with funds from Duke and the National Science Foundation (NSF), the National Phytotron was designed by leading scientists in controlled environment (CE) research and technology.
Controlled environment facilities permit investigators to create experimental systems in which biotic and/or abiotic variables and factors are controlled by the investigator. The phytotron can reproduce different types of environments, ranging from the arctic to the desert to the tropics. Researchers are able to maintain precise control over environmental conditions (e.g., soil type, air temperature, light levels, carbon dioxide (CO2) concentration, relative humidity, nutrients) and the organisms under study (e.g., mixtures of plant and animal species and their spatial arrangement). This provides the opportunity to gain increased understanding of the complex interactions between plants and their environment in studies of global change.
[This text adapted from the Phytotron website: http://www.biology.duke.edu/phytotron/]
Collection Overview
The Phytotron Records contain correspondence, memoranda, financial records, reports, grant proposals, blueprints, schematics, contracts, supplier catalogs, specification books, and ot er records of the planning and construction of the facility, as well as the operation of the Phytotron. These materials include a 1962 feasibility study, meeting minutes, construction progress reports, descriptions of phytotrons in business and academic settings, architect's reports, a facilities review, and records of the opening and dedication (1968), the Phytotron Board, the Regional Phytotron Committee, and USDA workshops.
Arrangement note
The records are organized by accession.
Related Material
Dept. of Botany records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Paul J. Kramer papers.
University Archives, Duke University.
Photographic files, Buildings: Phytotron.
University Archives, Duke University.
Greenhouses -- North Carolina; Greenhouses -- Design and construction; Global environmental change -- Research; Blueprints; Phytotron; Growth cabinets and rooms; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Duke University. Department of Botany; Duke University. Department of Botany; Duke University. Department of Biology
- Container List [A80-33]
  - Index of Material for Archives (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of reprints from research performed in the Phytotron (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1968-1969, 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Board Meetings of the Southeastern Plant Environment Labs, 1969 (Box 1)
  - SEPEL and the Duke Phytotron
    - Proposal for 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - SEPEL Brochure (Box 1)
    - Oak Ridge Associated Universities Newsletter (Box 1)
    - Utilities: Duke Unit of SEPEL, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - Breakdown of Operations for Duke Unit of SEPEL, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - Monies Collected on Space Charges for Duke Unit of SEPEL, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - The Amount and Cost of Space Used During September 1974 (Box 1)
    - Botany Departments in Southeast as of May 1975 (Box 1)
    - Foreign Grads and Post-doctoral Students Who Have Used Duke's Phytotron (Box 1)
    - Chamber Waiting List, Sept. 4, 1974-Oct. 22, 1974 (Box 1)
  - History of Phytotron (SEPEL)
    - SEPEL brochure (Duke and NC State Phytotron) (Box 1)
    - Article: SEPEL: New Phytotrons for Environmental Research (Box 1)
    - Article: Engineering Problems in the Design and Operation of Phytotrons (Box 1)
    - Article: Controlled Environments for Plant-Life Research (Box 1)
    - Letter: Henry Hellmers to Stephen C. Harward (Box 1)
    - Formal History: SEPEL The Southeastern Plant Environment Laboratories of Duke University and North Carolina State University (Box 1)
  - Report: Controlled-Climate Facilities, February 1959 (Box 2)
  - Controlled Environment-- Discussions and Committees, before 1962 (Box 2)
  - Phototron Proposal from Duke University and NC State University, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Proposal for SEPEL by Duke and NC State--effective 1 July 1967 (Box 2)
  - Proposal for SEPEL by Duke and NC State, 1 January 1973 - 31 December 1974 (Box 2)
  - Proposal for SEPEL by Duke, 1 January 1975 - 11 December 1975 (Box 2)
  - Biotrons Committee 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Site Visit (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Fred S. Dubin (Box 2)
  - Phytotron, Sept. 1975 (Box 3)
  - R.J. Downs Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Phytotron User's Committee (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Project Reviews (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Regional User's Committee (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Board (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Advisory Committee, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Advisory Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Phytotron Publicity (Box 3)
  - Atlanta (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Sievers, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
- 1993 Additions [A93-34, A93-35]
  - Southeastern Plant Environmental Laboratories (SEPEL) (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Concerning Duke's First Proposal, 1958-1960 (Box 4)
  - Phytotron -- Notes on 1st Duke Proposal (Box 4)
  - Hellmers (Box 4)
  - Schematic Stage Report to the Phytotron Board (Box 4)
  - Notes for Phytotron Planning, 1962-1963 (Evans, Senn, Lang, et al) (Box 4)
  - 2nd Duke Phytotron Planning Notes (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Correspondence, through February 1964 (Box 4)
  - Robert D. Rodwell and Associates (Box 4)
  - SEPEL: The Southeastern Plant Environment Laboratories of Duke University and North Carolina State University (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Planning Proposal (Box 4)
  - Phytotron History (Box 4)
  - Proposed Phytotron (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Costs (1st Duke Proposal), March 1959 (Box 4)
  - Engineers Memos, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Growth Chambers Misc. (Box 4)
  - Environmental Growth Chambers (Box 4)
  - Sherer-Gillett Installation (Box 4)
  - Percival -- Assembly and Operation (Box 4)
  - Greenhouse (Box 4)
  - Greenhouses and Equipment (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Expenditures (Box 4)
  - Memoranda on Phytotron (to Williams, etc.), 1964 (Box 4)
  - Lighting (Box 4)
  - Cornell Notes and Specifications (Box 4)
  - Windsor Plant Growth Chambers (Box 4)
  - Sugarcane Phytotron -- Brisbane (Box 4)
  - Notes on Phytotrons (Box 4)
  - Wisconsin (Box 4)
  - Phytotron, 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Duke's 1st Proposal (Box 4)
  - NASA 1962 (Box 4)
  - Bids (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Proposal and Grant Letters (Revised Budget, 1965-1966) (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Personnel, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Phytotron -- Agreement and Discussions, summer 1962 (Box 4)
  - Phytotron Materials and Equipment (Box 5)
  - Contract with Architects (Box 5)
  - Engineering Problems (Growth Chambers) (Box 5)
  - Phytotrons Historical and Informative (Box 5)
  - Information on other Phytotrons (Box 5)
  - Earhart Lab Cal Tech (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Lighting Information (Box 5)
  - NC State Unit (Memos) (Box 5)
  - Phytotron Costs Final Settlements (Box 5)
  - Construction Data (Box 5)
  - Opening of Phytotron (Box 5)
  - Opening of Phytotron (2nd folder) (Box 5)
  - Carter Williams (Box 5)
  - Construction Notes (Box 5)
  - Recorders from Cal Tech (Box 5)
  - Phytotron Expenditures (Box 5)
  - Construction Progress Reports 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Phytotron: Filing Code for Phytotron Correspondence (Box 5)
  - NC State Unive sity Phytotron 1968- (Box 5)
  - Phytotron Dedication (Box 5)
  - Phytotron Construction, August 1966-1969 (Box 5)
  - Phytotron Construction, Jan. 1965-July 1966 (Box 6)
  - Duke University Heating and Air conditioning, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Construction NC State Univ., Aug 1966-March 1967 (Box 6)
  - NC State University Phytotron Heating and Air-conditioning Contracts, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Construction NC State University, July 1965-July 1966 (Box 6)
  - Schematic Stage Report to the Phytotron Board, October 15, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Specifications, Spring 1965 (Box 6)
  - Schematic Stage Report to the Phytotron Board, November 1964 (Box 6)
  - Proposed Phytotron NC State University Raleigh, NC (Box 6)
  - Specifications Heating and Air Conditioning Two-Unit Phytotron (Box 6)
  - Specifications Two-Unit Phytotron (bound copy) (Box 6)
  - Board Meetings, 1974-1978 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Director 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - Regional Phytotron Committee Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Regional Phytotron Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Director, 1979-1983 (Box 6)
  - Southern Regional Education Board (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Staff and User Meetings, 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - USDA Workshop, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Workshop, 1975 (postponed) (Box 6)
  - Facilities Review, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Phytotron Research, 1970-1984 (Box 6)